Register of the Council for Inter-American Security records
Hoover Institution Archives
Council for Inter-American Security records
1975-1988
86013
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes (6.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, conference papers, memoranda, minutes, press releases, press summaries, and statistics relating to security requirements of various Latin American countries, especially in Central America; guerrilla activity in El Salvador; and a series of World Media Conferences on the media, especially in relation to formulation of American foreign policy. Includes statistics of incidences of violence in El Salvador and papers of Lynn Francis Bouchey, president of the Council.
Council for Inter-American Security.
Bouchey, L. Francis.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Founded in 1976 by Ronald Docksai and headed by Lynn Francis Bouchey from 1977 to 1992, the Council for Inter-American Security's (CIS) mission objective was to clarify the common security interests of Western Hemisphere nations, provide strategic advice for the protection of those interests, and disseminate its recommendations. Publications and analyses from CIS focused primarily on Latin American countries and provided data and statistics to Congress, the executive branch, and the American public.
In the early years of the Ronald Reagan administration, the organization was one of the more influential think tanks of the New Right, providing both policy and policymakers to the new administration. CIS also sponsored educational programs, seminars, conferences, and briefing sessions; conducted direct mail and advertising campaigns; and produced publications, radio shows, films, and television documentaries on various issues relating to foreign policy and national defense posture.
Scope and Content of Collection
The materials in the Council for Inter-American Security records, including correspondence, reports, conference papers, memoranda, minutes, press releases, press summaries, and statistics, were collected by Lynn Francis Bouchey during his time as president of the Council for Inter-American Security (CIS) from 1977 until his resignation in 1992. The collection focuses on security for Latin America countries such as El Salvador, Guatemala, Nicaragua, and countries in the Caribbean against Soviet and Communist infiltration and expansion.
The collection has been organized into ten series, and the original folder titles have been retained.
World Media Conference.; United States--Military relations--Latin America.; Latin America--Military relations--United States.; United States--Military relations--Central America.; Central America--Military relations--United States.; El Salvador--History--1979-1992.; Mass media.
- Lynn Francis Bouchey File, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Comprised of correspondence, travel records, projects, and notes of Lynn Francis Bouchey, arranged chronologically.
  - Lists: meetings, receptions, dinner, etc., 1977-1981 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Network notes, 1977 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Speech file, 1980s (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Omniplan chron, 1980 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 6-15)
  - Chron file for Annie, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Lynn projects, 1983 (Box-folder 1: 17)
- Conferences File, 1977-1988 (Boxes 1-5)
  Includes records on the sponsorship, production of, and participation in educational programs, seminars, conferences, symposiums, and briefing sessions during the final years of the Cold War. There are subseries on the Center for Liberation Strategy conference in 1986, the Inter-American Symposiums held annually between 1979 and 1981, the Geneva Conference in 1986, and World Media Conferences held consecutively between 1981 and 1983. The conferences cover topics relating to political and economic security between the United States and Latin American nations between 1977 and 1988. The subseries have been arranged alphabetically, then chronologically thereunder.
  - Center for Liberation Strategy, 1986-1988
    - General, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1: 18, Box-folder 2: 1-2)
    - Central America: Myths and Disinformation, 1980s (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Conference notes, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Board, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Brochures, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Finance proposal, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Saumer, France, 1988 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Inter-American Symposiums, 1977-1981
    - Brochures, 1977, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Programs, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Correspondence, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 11-12)
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 13-14)
    - Symposium biographies, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Simposio InterAmericano, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Symposium materials in Spanish, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Memo to participants, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Buenos Aires, Argentina, 1981 May (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Expenses, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Schedule, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Travel arrangements, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Acceptances, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Programs in English, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Programs in Spanish, 1979, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Lists, 1981 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Geneva, 1986
    - Colloquium - proposal and agendas (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - Colloquium - correspondence (Box-folder 3: 13)
    - Correspondence - names and addresses (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Judith Bingham correspondence (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - Conference documentation (Box-folder 3: 16)
    - Receipts - originals from US (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Conference - originals from Paris (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - World Media Conference, 1981-1983
    - 1981 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 4: 4-5)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Peru/Institute for Liberty and Democracy, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Education Institute: Jamaica Symposium Development, 1982 (Box-folder 4: 8-10)
  - Convention on National Defense (Leadership Foundation Convention), 1982 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Central America and the US Conference, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Conference/Santiago, Chile, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Central America Freedom Alliance Conference - human rights, 1983 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Institute on Religion and Democracy, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Paris/Central American Conference, 1985 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Debt Crisis Conference, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Privatization Conference, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - US-Colombian Legislative Conference on Narcotics Laws, Puerto Rico, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 5: 8)
- Correspondence, 1978-1987 (Boxes 5-6)
  Notable correspondents include Jean-Louis Clariond, Ambassador Robert H. McBride, Jack Skelly, Ambassador William Middendorf, Frank Calzon, Robert Reilly, and Congressional contacts. Arranged chronologically.
  - Coalition for Peace Through Strength, 1978 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - CIS mailings, 1979 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Editorial submissions - rejected, 1979 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Mailgrams, 1979 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Cuevas, Gustavo, 1979, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Clariond, Jean-Louis, 1979-1984 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - McBride, Robert H. (Ambassador), 1980 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Skelly, Jack, Cuba, 1980 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Coalition - correspondence media, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Cavallini, Raul, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Middendorf, William (Ambassador), 1981-1984 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Calzon, Frank, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Letter from Richardson to Weyrich, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - Reilly, Robert, 1982 (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - Hamilton, Scott, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - Young, Peter, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Grassroots correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Congressional contacts, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - Items for Jose Robelo, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 28)
  - Mail from Haiti, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 1)
- Financial Documents, 1981-1987 (Box 6)
  - Council for Inter-American Security invoices, 1981 (Box-folder 6: 2-4)
  - Central America trip (travel records), 1985 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - US Information Agency grant, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 6)
- Memoranda, 1977-1987 (Boxes 6-7)
  - Board of Directors, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Coalition for a Democratic Majority, 1978 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Executive Committee, 1979 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Memos, 1979 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - CIS Business Bureau, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Association of American Chambers of Commerce in Latin America, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - The Fraser Institute, 1980 (Box-folder 6: 13)
  - Metro Graphics Inc., 1981 (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - Advisors - Admiral and Generals, 1981 (Box-folder 6: 15)
  - Paraguayan-American Development Co., 1981 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Coalition for Free Elections in El Salvador, 1982 (Box-folder 6: 17)
  - Coalition for Democracy in Central America, 1984 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Costa Rica Action Plan for Tom Miller, 1986 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Frank Madsen, 1987 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Organizations File, 1980-1986 (Box 7)
  Includes files on organizations that worked in conjunction with the CIS, such as the Central American Working Group (CAWG), Organization of American States (OAS), Asamblea Nicaraguense Unidad Democrática, Central American Program of Undergraduate Scholarship (CAMPUS), and Unión del Centro Democrático.
  - Central American Working Group, 1980-1984
    - Q and A on El Salvador, 1980s (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - Proposal, 1980s (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - National Council of World Affairs Organizations, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - Washington College speaker, 1981 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - Outreach Working Group on C.A., 1983 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - Lists, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Organization of American States, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Asamblea Nicaraguense Unidad Democrática, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Central American Program of Undergraduate Scholarships, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Unión del Centro Democrático, 1986 (Box-folder 7: 13)
- Project File, 1980-1988 (Boxes 7-9)
  - Abraham Guillen, 1980s (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Caribbean Central American Action, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Castro Research Project, 1980 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - National Council of Churches, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Centro de Estudios Publicos, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - National Center for Pan-Am Studies, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - National Coalition for America's Survival, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 20)
  - Lex Ritter/Costa Rica, 1984 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Resume: Rafael Rosario, ADO, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - The Caribbean and Latin American Scholarship Program, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Memoria del Encuentro Intercooperativo, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Briefing book for Dwight Ink, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Nicaraguan Refugee Fund, 1985 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - African Studies Center - notes, 1986 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - "The Transition to Democracy in Central America,", 1988 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - "The Role of the Military in the Transition of Democracy," Spain, 1988 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Oliver North: Declassified, 1988 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    Materials related to a video on North.
- Reports, 1977-1988 (Boxes 9-14)
  Includes statistical reports of acts of violence between 1979 and 1984 relating to guerilla activity during the civil war in El Salvador. Additional reports relating to agro-industrial development and cold war political-economic relations are also included.
  - Acts of Violence reports, 1979-1984
    - 1979 (Box-folder 9: 2-3)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 9: 4-5)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 9: 6-8)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 10: 4-5, Box-folder 11: 1-2)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 11: 3-6, Box-folder 12: 1-2)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - National Economic Development Association, 1977 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - Council for Inter-American Security - security survey, 1978 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Members of Congress for Peace Through Law, 1979 (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - "Annual Report, Foreign and Domestic Corporations,", 1979 (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - "The Political Situation in Colombia in Recent Years,", 1980s (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - "Understanding of the Problem,", 1980s (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - A Primer on Communism, 1980s (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - "The Impact of Small Economies on Metropolitan Countries of Different Economic Systems,", 1980s (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - Banco Agricola, 1980 (Box-folder 12: 12)
  - Citizens Commission on the Crisis in the Americas, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - Foreign Broadcast Information Service El Salvador war toll, 1983 (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - Justification de Implementacion, 1983 (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Executive Summary on Dominican Republic, 1983 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - El Salvador/special report, 1984 (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - Manual de Codigos, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - "Is There a Future for Foreign Aid?,", 1985 (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - Costa Rica - recent economic developments, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - "The Activites and Operations of the Institute for Price Stabilization of the Dominican Republic,", 1985 (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - "Agricultural Sector Overview,", 1985 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - "Diagnostico de los Sistemas de Manejo Postproducción de Granos Basicos en Costa Rica,", 1985 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - Centro para Investigaciones, 1985 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - Interview, 1985 (Box-folder 14: 3)
  - Mercado Agroindustria: Costa Rica, 1985 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - "Obstacles to US-USSR Arms Negotiations and a Viable Approach for the Future,", 1985 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - Nicaraguan Freedom Campaign - human rights, media, 1986 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - "Political-Economic Dynamics of Marketing Boards in Latin America,", 1986 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - "Postharvest Grain System Research and Development,", 1986 (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - Gedes Voluntary Report, 1986 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - "Patterns of Conflicts,", 1986 (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - "Dismantling Soviet Global Strategy,", 1987 (Box-folder 14: 11)
  - "Central America and the Hemispheric Security,", 1988 (Box-folder 14: 12)
- Research File, 1980-1988 (Box 15)
  - Bibliography Task Force, 1980s (Box-folder 15: 1)
  - Guatemala trip - general, 1980s (Box-folder 15: 2)
  - "The U.S. Media and the Nicaraguan Revolution,", 1980s (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - José de Meira Penna, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - Guatemala, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 15: 5-6)
  - Caribbean Basin Initiative, Program Cruise, 1988 (Box-folder 15: 7)
- Printed Matter, 1975-1988 (Boxes 15-17)
  - Articles, 1978, 1980
    - Direct mail possiblities, 1978 (Box-folder 15: 8)
    - Capitalism and Christianity, 1980 (Box-folder 15: 9)
  - Brochures, 1980s
    - Cypress International, 1980s (Box-folder 15: 10)
    - International Education: Cornerstone of Competition, 1986 (Box-folder 15: 11)
    - Resistance International, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 15: 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1978-1987
    - Terrorism book, 1978 (Box-folder 15: 13)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 15: 14)
    - 1979-1980 (Box-folder 15: 15)
    - The New York Times, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 15: 16)
    - La Republica, La Nacion, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 15: 17)
    - La Republica, 1986 (Box-folder 15: 18)
    - Africa, 1987 (Box-folder 16: 1-4)
  - Press releases, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - The MX Project, 1979 (Box-folder 16: 6)
  - Navarro articles, 1979 (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - News release, 1980 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - Press release, 1980 (Box-folder 16: 9)
  - Council for Inter-American Security, publications press and advertisements, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 16: 10)
  - Pamphlets, 1975-1986
    Pamphlets collected while traveling between conferences in Latin America and Europe relating to the socio-political atmosphere of the 1980s between the Western and Eastern hemispheres. Arranged chronologically.
    - Anhelos, 1975 (Box-folder 16: 11)
    - Proceedings of a Multinational Conference on NATO and the Global Threat, 1978 (Box-folder 16: 12)
    - Ethics and Public Policy Reprint 18: Alienation and US Foreign Policy, 1979 (Box-folder 16: 13)
    - Ethics and Public Policy Reprint 19: The Cost of America's Retreat, 1979 (Box-folder 16: 14)
    - Estatutos, 1979 (Box-folder 16: 15)
    - Money, Investment and Growth in Latin America, 1979 (Box-folder 16: 16)
    - Nacionalismo y Integracion, 1979 (Box-folder 16: 17)
    - You Won't Get Spanked in Sweden, 1980s (Box-folder 16: 18)
    - Nicaraguan Democratic Union, 1980 (Box-folder 16: 19)
    - America Latina y La Crisis de Combustible, 1980 (Box-folder 16: 20)
    - Less Is More: Cutting Marginal Income Tax Rates, 1981 (Box-folder 17: 1)
    - The US Defence Mobilization Infrastructure Problems and Priorities, 1981 (Box-folder 17: 2)
    - How Realistic Is the Nuclear Freeze Proposal?, 1982 (Box-folder 17: 3)
    - Our Moral Duty to Defend Freedom, 1983 (Box-folder 17: 4)
    - Topicos de Actualidad, 1983 (Box-folder 17: 5)
    - Instituto de Formación Política del Partido Reformista, 1983 December (Box-folder 17: 6)
    - Instituto de Formación Política del Partido Reformista, 1984 September (Box-folder 17: 7)
    - Central America: The Future of the Democratic Revolution, 1984 (Box-folder 17: 8)
    - Instituto de Formación Política del Partido Reformista, 1985 January (Box-folder 17: 9)
    - Instituto de Formación Política del Partido Reformista, 1985 May (Box-folder 17: 10)
    - Economic Systems and Economic Ethics, 1985 (Box-folder 17: 11)
    - Misión Cumplida, 1986 (Box-folder 17: 12)